Samuel M. Wilson Presbyterian Church Photographic Collection, ca. 1903-1933 PA50W2
University of Kentucky Special Collections
Samuel M. Wilson Presbyterian Church Photographic Collection
ca. 1903-1933
PA50W2
University of Kentucky Special Collections
0.25 Cubic feet 1 box: 19 images
The Samuel M. Wilson Presbyterian Church Photographic Collection (.25 cubic feet, 19 images in 1 box; dated ca. 1903-1933) consists of nineteen black and white silver prints of various Presbyterian churches and the Synodial Presbyterian Orphanage in Anchorage, Kentucky.
Conditions Governing Access note
The collection is open to researchers by appointment.
Biographical Note
Judge Samuel Mackay Wilson (1871-1946) was a Lexington attorney and author, noted for his meticulous scholarship and precise writing style. He was also a collector of books, manuscripts, maps, and photographs. Wilson's main area of interest was early Kentucky history.
Wilson's most famous case was his defense of Kentucky Secretary of State Caleb Powers. Powers was charged in connection with the assassination of Kentucky Governor William Goebel in 1899. After serving as a judge-advocate during World War I, Wilson returned to Kentucky, where he established a successful law practice.
Judge Wilson served on numerous civic commissions, where he was active in historical preservation. Wilson played an important role in the preservation of the Henry Clay Estate, Blue Licks Battlefield, and Fort Boonesboro.
Wilson organized the Cakes and Ale Club, an annual gathering of Lexingtonians interested in book collecting. He was also a member of the Book Thieves, an organization of local historians and educators who were influential in the creation and development of Special Collections and Archives at the University of Kentucky.
After Wilson's death in 1946, his extensive collection of books, photographs, and personal papers were donated to the University of Kentucky. The Wilson Collection is the foundation on which Special Collections and Archives has been built. Following Mrs. Wilson's death in 1959, the items which she had retained were added to the collection.
Scope and Contents note
The Samuel M. Wilson Presbyterian Church Photographic Collection (.25 cubic feet, 19 images in 1 box; dated ca. 1903-1933) consists of nineteen black and white silver prints of various Presbyterian churches and the Synodial Presbyterian Orphanage (Bellewood Presbyterian Home for Children) in Anchorage, Kentucky.
Related Archival Materials note
Bull, Jacqueline. The Samuel M. Wilson Library. Perry Publishing Co.: Frankfort, KY.
Clark, Thomas D. The Book Thieves of Lexington: A Reminiscence. The Kentucky Review. v.2 (Winter 1984): 27-45.
PA50W2: Samuel M. Wilson: Presbyterian Church Photographic Collection, ca. 1880-1940, University of Kentucky Special Collections.
50W38: Samuel M. Wilson Papers, 1792-1945, University of Kentucky Special Collections.
PA51W13: Samuel M. Wilson: Kentucky Sesquicentennial Photographic Collection, 1942, University of Kentucky Special Collections.
51W20: Samuel M. Wilson: World War I papers, 1916-1941, University of Kentucky Special Collections.
51W54: M. Wilson Library Records, 1900-1946, University of Kentucky Special Collections.
61W12: Samuel M. Wilson Clippings, 1895-1946, University of Kentucky Special Collections.
PA62W8: Samuel M. Wilson: Picture Collection, ca. 1840-1959,University of Kentucky Special Collections.
PA73W4: Samuel M. Wilson: Burt and Brabb Lumber Company Photographic Collection, ca. 1900, University of Kentucky Special Collections.
51W19: Samuel Ramsey Wilson Papers, 1835-1885, University of Kentucky Special Collections.
49W1: Samuel M. Wilson Collection on Kentucky, 1715-1936, University of Kentucky Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift
Synodial Presbyterian Orphanage (Anchorage, Ky.).; Wilson, Samuel M. (Samuel Mackay), 1871-1946; black-and-white photographs; gelatin silver prints; Kentucky--Church history.; Presbyterian Church--Kentucky.
- Architecture, Series I.
  - "Side view of Union 'meeting house'"; graves on 3 sides of the church., 11/23/1933 (Box 1, Item 1)
    General note
    (2x3) b&w print
  - "Union 'meeting house'; about 1.5 miles west of Brumfield, KY (station on the L & N Railroad in Boyle County) and about .25 miles south of Danville-Lebanon Pike. Dr. Thos. Cleland and Rev. Joshua Wilson ordrained where Oct.1804-See Page 87. Life of Dr. Thos. Cleland. 11/22/33", 11/22/1933 (Box 1, Item 2)
  - "What remains of the house of Dr. Thos. Cleland and wife, Margaret Armstrong Cleland; known as 'School of the Prophets' on New Providence Cemetery Road. McAfee, Ky. House finished September, 1813. 11/23/1933" (Box 1, Item 3)
  - "Hopewell Presbyterian Church" 1787, [n.d.] (Box 1, Item 4)
    (5x7) b&w print
  - "Synodial Presbyterian Orphanage; Anchorage, KY. Doll house, Little girls; given by a Mr. Vanderbilt" (Box 1, Item 5)
    (3x4) b&w print on cardboard backing
  - At the Orphanage: "Laundry built of old brick from Bellewood School" (Box 1, Item 6)
  - At the Orphanage: "Supt. Robert G. Haney, House, part of old Bellewood School;" Man in front of house, [n.d.] (Box 1, Item 7)
  - At the Orphanage: "House of Supt. Bevy of Girls, Corner of the Girls' Dormitory;" Young women in front of house, corner of dormitory in view., [n.d.] (Box 1, Item 8)
  - At the Orphanage: "Boys' Dormitory, Old Brick, Mrs. Watt; Matron", [n.d.] (Box 1, Item 9)
  - At the Orphanage: "Little Girls Dormitory, Main Building; Old Post Office; Kitchen; Dining Room, Cellar, Refrigerator." Children's slide on left. (Box 1, Item 10)
  - At the Orphanage: "Barn; dairy stalls, farm implements; potato bins" (Box 1, Item 11)
  - At the Orphanage: "Farmer's House; smoke house with 20 hams being cured", [n.d.] (Box 1, Item 12)
  - At the Orphanage: "Boys' Dormitory, constructed of old brick from the Bellwood School Bldg.", [n.d.] (Box 1, Item 13)
  - At the Orphanage: "Girls' Dormitory, Bevy Girls, Boone Building; Provided by W.G. Duncan. Memorial to his sister, Ms. Boone." Group of girls in front of house., [n.d.] (Box 1, Item 14)
  - "Presbyterian Church nearby; where the children and all worship." (Box 1, Item 15)
  - Public School; Anchorage, KY where all the children attend school." (Box 1, Item 16)
- Portrait, Series II.
  - Dr. Thomas Cleland (Box 1, Item 17)
  - "Picture of the old 'Mulberry Church', in Shelby County, Ky. at which Rev. Dr. Sam'l R. Wilson was pastor from 1863 to 1865. Copied by 'Muller, Photographer' from original photograph, belonging to Mr. Joseph A. Logan, of Christians. Copies obtained January 12, 1903. The building shown is no longer standing, having been torn down and a new building erected on a slightly different site in 1894-1895. Sam'l M. Wilson". People in front of church. (Box 1, Item 18)
    (8x10) b&w print
- Oversize, Series III.
  - A group picture on two separate photos with very wide angle lens, [n.d.] (Folder 1, Item 19)
    oversize photo